Welcome back.
So you completed an assignment on defining what is a project.
We've talked about what a project is and probably based on your experience you already have a great
idea of what a project is.
But now let's talk about the other part of that equation.
If we have projects we need Project Management.
So what is project management.
Did you find yourself at a party and someone says Oh so what do you do.
And then you say project manager and like what it sounded like you said you're a project manager.
Or they're like OK so what does that mean you're a project manager.
What does that mean.
That's my favorite one.
Like what is that.
So a project manager is an individual who manages projects while the project manager is an individual
who manages the change in organizations that it manages the change from moving from the current state
to that desired future state.
And all the logistics and all the different parts of that organization that are touched by that change.
That's how I always describe it for your exam.
Project management is the application of the knowledge the skills the tools and techniques to meet the
project requirements.
So people still don't get it sometimes or a project manager is.
So I say OK you're going to build a house.
Right.
We're going to build the house and you've got this vision of a house.
Why have to extract the requirements from you have to really have your vision.
We have to be in sync with that vision of what you want me to create.
So that's the first part I have to understand what you want now as the PM.
I have to do all the logistics.
So you think about all of the permits and the blueprints and the laborers that have that skill set to
do the foundation and the framing and electrical and so on and all those moving parts that have to sync
up and work together to be cost effective to help us create a profit and to create exactly the thing
that you want as a result of the project.
There are 49 49 project management processes that I would utilize in that scenario.
So there are things I would do in initiating the processes from planning to execute.
Obviously we're going to monitor and control and then at some point we're going to close out that project
and your house is done.
So that's a clean way to describe what a project manager does.
So Project Management utilizes all of those processes as needed.
Do you have to use every single process in the Timbuktu you have to use all 14:9 processes.
No you don't.
If I'm not buying anything in my project I sure don't need to do procurement if I have a low priority
project I may not have to do quantitative risk analysis.
I only do the processes that are needed in that project.
So we'll talk more about that coming up.
Typical project management is when we're talking about identifying requirements.
So I want to build a house for you or you hire my company to build the house I need to gather requirements
I need to really understand what you want us to create.
Then I have two of the projects in motion.
Address your needs and concerns and also expectations.
So while you might have a vision that I don't quite understand or the expectation is OK we're going
to build a swimming pool but we're not paying to fill the water you're going to have to get somebody
to do that.
So you know kind of a mismatch there so we aren't clear.
We have to set up and maintain and carry out communications bulk of the PM's job is communicating managing
stakeholders like an in-house project.
The stakeholders there are more than just the homeowner that we're building the house for.
It's also the project team the contractors the vendors the city inspectors maybe even the neighbors
around the house project.
So they're all stakeholders.
Anyone that can affect the project or is affected by the project is a stakeholder and then we have to
balance competing project constraints and the big ones.
You have scope quality schedule.
The cost of the budget the resources physical and human and risk.
So those are competing project constraints.
Typically we think of the iron triangle though that you think of time cost and scope that those are
the three big constraints.
But we also have to think about quality and quality can be affected and the resources and then risk
is one that we have to balance because they can certainly affect the other constraints a term you should
be familiar with.
And really I've described it in this house project is progressive elaboration progressive elaboration
is where I start very broadly deductive reasoning I start very broad and I get more and more and more
information until I'm very specific.
So when that house project the homeowner says well what's this going to cost me.
That's the first question right.
Like any stakeholder.
Well I can give a you know I guess a swag if you will.
A wild guess.
And so they ask I said well it's probably going to be around five hundred thousand dollars and they
say will probably how much is that.
And of course we can get more specific later in the course.
So I want you more for Maisha what type of floors do you want what type of cabinets do you want what
type of appliances what type of material.
And so as I get more and more information I can give an estimate with much more confidence.
Now we'll talk more about cost estimating going on when we get to Chapter 7 and have him back just giving
an idea of progressive elaboration that I can start with an idea or a concept begin to formulate the
idea through requirements gathering maybe a business case is why we're investing is this what's the
value that's created.
Do I need to do a feasibility study.
And then I get to the project.
But that's an example of progressive elaboration.
Anytime I start broad and get more and more specific I'm elaborating as I have more information to elaborate
upon.
All right great job.
Keep moving forward.
I'll see you in the next lecture.